<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Andrew Murray</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Andrew Murray</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Earth Science Coding Network</title>
      <link>/post/escn/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/escn/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;div class=&#34;line-block&#34;&gt;      We are excited to announce the Earth Science Coding Network, a new working group to bring together those at Duke, NC State, and UNC Chapel Hill who code as part of their work in Earth Sciences. Our goal is to promote inter-institutional community building and provide a communication space for those of us who are working through similar problems. We’ll hold a regular meeting dedicated to coding. This will feel like a writing workshop but for code!&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;line-block&#34;&gt;     Reserved space will be provided at all three institutions simultaneously and we will connect through video conferencing (Zoom), allowing us to interact without actually having to leave campus. The idea is for participants to dedicate this time to accomplishing a coding task they have. We will start with quick introductions and goal setting and then move into individual work. We hope you will consider joining us and find it a productive space to work in while networking and building community. All academic and coding levels are encouraged to participate!&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSeoBuqsvVCfZt_vkb8gJtVB6BTEIvCsRvFJ_pGDr6FqqS3zeg/viewform&#34;&gt;Sign up to be on the email list here!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have questions feel free to reach out to one of us!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Duke: &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:ury.emily@gmail.com?subject=Earth%20Science%20Coding%20Network&#34;&gt;Emily Ury&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NC State: &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:ssaia@ncsu.edu?subject=Earth%20Science%20Coding%20Network&#34;&gt;Sheila Saia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UNC: &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:armurray@live.unc.edu?subject=Earth%20Science%20Coding%20Network&#34;&gt;Andrew Murray&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Climate Game Changers</title>
      <link>/post/endeavors/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/endeavors/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Check out the story on our field work in Ecuador this past summer as it appears in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://endeavors.unc.edu/climate-game-changers/&#34;&gt;UNC endeavors magazine&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vulnerability to Domestic Wells from Hydraulic Fracturing</title>
      <link>/post/vulnerability-to-domestic-wells-from-hydraulic-fracturing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/vulnerability-to-domestic-wells-from-hydraulic-fracturing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;##Update&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Follow along with my research on understanding domestic wells at risk to effects from methane migration stemming from hydraulic fracturing activity. &lt;a href=&#34;https://amurraygeo.com/project/domestic-wells-and-fracking/&#34;&gt;This living document&lt;/a&gt; is being created in the spirit of open and reproducible research. Most of the analysis is done with the R statistical language and is presented exactly as executed. All of the data is free and publicly accessible. This will allow others to reproduce everything exactly, or plug in their own data. It also allows others to offer critiques or feedback on the methods.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
